Register of the World War I subject collection
Hoover Institution Archives
- Oversize Materials, 1894, 1911-1926, 1933 (Boxes 35-42, map case)
  - Poster, "Well Done My Boys - Welcome Home,", 1919
    Triangular paper American flag.
  - Map Case, 1882, 1894, 1911-1925 (Map-case 1-19)
    Unless otherwise specified, the items in this subseries are maps.
    - Road Map, U.S. 3rd Army, 1918 (Map-case 1)
    - Rand McNally War Map of the British Front, undated
      "A Strategic Map of the Battle Ground in Belgium and France, from Ostend to St. Quentin, Compiled from the Latest Military Maps of the Army Staffs in Washington, London, and Paris, and from Other Official Sources." Has handwritten/drawn annotations.
    - Rand McNally War Map of the French Front, Southern Section, circa 1917 September
      "A Strategic Map of the Battle Ground in Northern France, from St. Mihiel to the Swiss Border, Showing the farthest advance of the Germans in 1914 and the battle line in September, 1917, Compiled from the latest Military Maps of the Army Staffs in Washington, London, and Paris, and from other Official Sources."
    - Map to Illustrate the Offensive of the St. Mihiel Salient, 1918
      From "Maps Pertaining to Report of General John J. Pershing, U.S.A.;" intended to accompany Pershing's report of 20 November 1918, which can be found in Box 4, Folder 27.
    - Map to Illustrate the Meuse-Argonne Offensive, First, Second and Last Phases, 1918
    - Major Offensive and Defensive Operations, 1920 May
      From the General Headquarters of the American Expeditionary Forces.
    - Daily Mail Map of the Battlefields of France, 1919
    - Flemmings Spezialkarte der Südlichen Westfront, circa 1918 October
    - Streifenkarte No. VIII/IX, circa 1918 September
      Shows the German army position in the area of Benay and Essigny-le-Grand, France.
    - Map Showing Boundaries of First and Second Armies, Aug. 29th - Nov. 11th 1918, 1920
    - Order of Battle on Western Front 11 A.M., Nov. 11, 1918, circa 1918 November
    - Fronte des Armees en France et en Belgique, undated
    - Carte de France, circa 1918
      Includes battle fronts, enemy lines, and progress of the Allies.
    - Poland, 1920 March
    - Carte Schématique du Canevas d'Ensemble/Scheme of Triangulation and Traverse, 1918 July
    - Hand drawn, untitled map, undated
      Includes a section labeled Exerzier Platz. Presumably German.
    - "Just One Day with the G-2-C Bottle [sic] Scarred Veterans of the Battle of Chaumont,", undated
      Cartoons printed on top of a map.
    - Ravensteins Kriegskarte vom Südlichen Balkan und Klein-Asien, dem Russisch-Türkisch-Persischen Kriegsschauplatz, und Spezialkarten der Gallipoli und dem Bosporus, circa 1915 (Map-case 2)
    - Ravensteins Kriegskarte des Kampfgebietes: Bapaume, Albert, Amiens, Roye, Noyon (Kriegskarte Nr. 34), circa 1916
    - Ravensteins Kriegskarte des Kampfgebietes: Arras, Loretto, La Bassé, Lille (Kriegskarte Nr. 35), circa 1916
    - Ravensteins Kriegskarte des Kampfgebietes: St. Mihiel, Pont à Moussons, Toul, Nancy, Senones (Kriegskarte Nr. 37), circa 1916
    - Ravensteins Kriegskarte für das Gebiet zwischen Gent und Calais, Lille u. Zeebrügge (Kriegskarte Nr. 43), circa 1917
    - Ravensteins Kriegskarte für das Gebiet zwischen Gent u. Dünkirchen, Lille u. Zeebrügge (Kriegskarte Nr. 43), circa 1917
    - Belgium and France, Sheet 19 S.E., Second Edition, 1915
    - Belgium [Roulers], Sheet 20, undated
    - Trench Map, Belgium, Sheet 20 N.W., Edition 2A, 1917 June
    - Trench Map, Belgium, Sheet 20 S.W., Edition 3A, 1917 May
    - Belgium and France, Sheet 27 N.E., Second Edition, 1916
    - Belgium and France, Sheet 27, Edition 2, 1917 May
    - Belgium and France, Sheet 28, Edition 3, 1917 February
    - Trench Map, Belgium, Sheet 28 N.W., Edition 6A, 1917 July
    - Carte Routière pour Automobilistes et Cyclistes - Nord-Est de la France, undated (Map-case 3)
    - Carte Routière pour Automobilistes et Cyclistes - Environs de Paris, Section Nord-Est, undated
    - Carte Routière pour Automobilistes et Cyclistes - Environs de Paris, Section Nord-Ouest, undated
    - Carte Routière pour Automobilistes et Cyclistes - Environs de Paris, Section Sud-Est, undated
    - Nouvelle Carte de France, Belgique, Bords du Rhin, Suisse, etc., undated
    - Map of the Western Theatre of War, 1918
      Prepared in the Map Department of the National Geographic Society for the National Geographic Magazine.
    - Philips' Large-Scale Contoured Map of the Anglo-French Front - The Western German Frontier and the Line of the Rhine, circa 1917 June
    - Philips' Large Scale Strategical War Map of Europe - Western Area, undated
    - Carte de France, 1894 (Map-case 4)
    - [Argonne, France], circa 1918
      According to a handwritten note on the back, this map was used in the Argonne, after 2 November 1918.
    - [Northern France], undated
      Has a handwritten note on the front that says "Vassy." According to a handwritten note on the back, this map was used on a march from St. Mihiel to the Argonne.
    - Zusammendruck III Nord, [France], 1916
    - Zusammendruck XVII, [France], 1918 June
    - Alençon, undated
    - Altkirch - Carte générale des Objectifs d'Artillerie, 1925
      1er Juillet 1918. Originally printed in 1918; this version is a reprint.
    - Amiens, 1914
    - Argonne - Montfaucon - Etain - Vendresse - Mouzon, 1925
      Originally printed in 1918; this version is a reprint. A.E.F. G-2, First Army, graphic summary of enemy activity, 1 November 1918.
    - Breteuil, 1918 December 18
    - Brimont, undated
    - Châlons, 1911
    - Château-Thierry, 1918 August 7
    - Cheminot, 1917 September
    - Commercy, 1912
    - Crépy-en-Valois-Epernay-Coulommiers, 1918 May
    - Dun-sur-Meuse, 1918
      Tirage du 20 Août 1918, 4e Edition.
    - Dun-sur-Meuse, Edition du 5 Octobre 1918
    - Dun-sur-Meuse, 1918
      Tirage du 6 Octobre 1918, 5e Edition.
    - Etain - Carte générale des Objectifs d'Artillerie a la date du 24 Août 1918, 1924
      Tirage du 3 Août 1918, 40e Edition. Originally printed in 1918; this version is a reprint.
    - Forêt d'Argonne - Carte générale des Objectifs d'Artillerie a la date du 9 Septembre 1918, 1924
      Tirage du 23 Juillet 1918, 11e Edition. Originally printed in 1918; this version is a reprint.
    - Lille, 1914 (Map-case 5)
    - Metz, 1912
    - Montdidier S.O., 1914
    - Montdidier-Ost, 1918 February
    - Mort Mare, 1918
    - Nancy, 1912
    - Pannes and Xivray, 1917
    - Pont-a-Mousson, Croquis No. 1, 1918 July
      According to a handwritten note, it is an artillery map of the Pont-a-Mousson sector when it was occupied by the 1st Artillery Brigade.
    - Sainte-Aulde, undated
    - St. Mihiel B, 1924
      Tirage du 19 Août 1918, 9e Edition. Originally printed in 1918; this version is a reprint. Handwritten note on the back indicates that on 12 September 1918 St. Mihiel was overrun and captured by the American First Army.
    - St. Mihiel C, 1924
      Tirage du 9 Juin 1918, 9e Edition. Originally printed in 1918; this version is a reprint.
    - Thiaucourt, Gruppe Groz., circa 1918 April
    - Thiaucourt, Gruppe Groz., Artillerie-Wochenkarte, 1918 May
    - Verdun, 1911
    - Verdun, 1913
    - Verdun, Planmaterial der 3. Armee, 1918 September
    - Verdun A, 1918
      Tirage du 12 Août 1918, 28e Edition.
    - Verdun A - Carte générale des Objectifs d'Artillerie a la date du 9 Septembre 1918, 1924
      Tirage du 12 Août 1918, 28e Edition. Originally printed in 1918; this version is a reprint.
    - Verdun B, 1918
      Tirage du 1 Septembre 1918, 35e Edition.
    - Verdun B - Carte générale des Objectifs d'Artillerie a la date du 9 Septembre 1918, 1924
      Tirage du 1 Septembre 1918, 35e Edition. Originally printed in 1918; this version is a reprint.
    - Vosges, undated
    - Vosges, circa 1918 July
    - Wassy, 1913
    - Gravelotte, 1882 (Map-case 6)
      "Zu: Griepenkerl, taktische Unterrichtsbriefe, 5. Auflage." For prints of digital photos taken of the map, see Box 32, Folder 29.
    - Poster, "An Meine Völker!,", 1916 November
    - Poster, "Seine kaiserliche und königlich Apostolische Majestät…,", 1914 July 4
    - Maps, Enemy Order of Battle, First Army, American Expeditionary Forces, No. 124, 1919 (Map-case 7-14)
      These maps depict the Western Front from 1 September 1918 to 11 November 1918.
    - Maps, Graphic Summary of Enemy Activity, First Army, American Expeditionary Forces, No. 124, 1919 (Map-case 15-18)
      These maps depict the Western Front from 1 October 1918 to 11 November 1918.
    - Amiens, 1916 October (Map-case 19)
      Handwritten notes on back: "British Military maps, Somme complete, 1916." "British War Office Official Map. Amiens - Peronne area. Scene of British 5th Army retreat, March and April 1918. This map is heavily taped. However, given that it is an officially produced map without annotations, the decision was made to not take extensive preservation action.
    - Lens, 1916
      Handwritten notes on back: "British Military maps, 1916, Doullens-Arras Bapaume areas." "Official Map - Doullens-Bapaume area. Scene of trench digging and wiring activity April 1918 by entire regiment between Terra Mesnil and Le Val de Maison." This map is heavily taped. However, given that it is an officially produced map without annotations, the decision was made to not take extensive preservation action.
    - St. Quentin, 1918 October
      Handwritten notes on back: "World War One map, British Front, vicinity St. Quentin." "British War Office Official Map. Roisel-Tincourt, St. Quentin areas." This map is heavily taped. However, given that it is an officially produced map without annotations, the decision was made to not take extensive preservation action.
    - Valenciennes, 1916 April
      Handwritten notes on back: "British Military maps, 1916. Cambrai attack 11/20/1917, German counterattack 11/30/1917." "British War Office Official Map. Fins-Gouzeaucourt, Cambrai area. Cambrai Offensive 11/20/17, Cambrai Defensive 11/30/17, Somme Defensive 3/21/18." This map is heavily taped. However, given that it is an officially produced map without annotations, the decision was made to not take extensive preservation action.
- Memorabilia, circa 1914-1922 (Boxes 43-44)
  - Backgammon board made by a Bulgarian soldier during World War I, undated (Box 43)
  - Food Administration apron arm badges, 1917 (Box 44)
  - Two samples of materials of German sand bags, circa 1918
    A note with the samples reads: "These materials are of woven paper fiber in place of yute, of which supply was exhausted. These materials were picked up in 1918 just across the German line in the Meuse Argonne area."
  - Small banner - Flags of the Victorious Nations in the War to Make the World Safe for Democracy, undated
  - American Red Cross service cap and insignia/buttons from member of Stanford Unit, undated
  - Plaster of Paris bas relief of the Bruxelles City Hall, 1916
  - World War I European canteen token, Royal Arsenal Cooperative Society, undated
  - Comrades of the Great War lapel pin, undated
  - Buttons [eagle], undated
    Two buttons - one large, one small.
  - Get Behind the Government - Liberty Loan of 1917 pin
  - Liberty Loan pin, 1917-1918
  - Victory pin, circa 1918
    Pin features crossed United States flags with portraits of President Woodrow Wilson and General John J. Pershing, as well as a red, white and blue ribbon that hangs from the pin.
  - Remember the Lusitania - Buy Liberty Bonds cardboard bottle cap, 1917-1918
  - Third Liberty Loan pin, circa 1918
  - U.S. War Savings Service tag with cloth tie, circa 1917-1918
  - Reel of microfilm from The British Library, 1914-1917
  - Decorative handkerchief - Wir halten fest und treu zusammen, undated
  - Decorative handkerchief - Beschiessung der Festung Namur, undated
  - Armband - Vaterländischer Hilfsdienst, undated
    See also: Kriegsamt (Vaterländische Hilfsdienst), Box 17, folder 14.
  - United States Navy insignia, Chief Petty Officer - Artificer Branch - Chief Storekeeper, undated
    The title (Chief Storekeeper) was changed from Chief Yeoman in October 1916.
  - Playing cards, undated
    Three decks. Two are boxed: Deutschlands grosse Söhne and Unsere Fürsten und Heerführer.
  - Russian calendars, 1922
    Two 1922 page-a-day tear-away calendars. In Russian.
  - Russian puppets, circa 1914
    Four paper puppets (a kind of hybrid between a paper doll and a marionette -- largely one-dimensional, but with moving parts) of Russian soldiers.
  - Brown chevron arm patch, undated
  - Italian interpreter's badge, undated
    According to a typed note accompanying the badge, it was worn by Italians whose familiarity with English enabled them to interpret and translate for American soldiers in Italy.
  - League of the Cross Cadets War Veteran ribbon, undated
  - Welcome Home 33rd Division U.S.A. ribbon, circa 1919
    Compliments of the John Bressmen Company.
- Microfilm reel (Reel 1)
  Reel includes a variety of World War I materials: Warcyclopedia, 1919; congressional bills, executive orders, newspaper clippings, and other collected materials, 1917-1919.